<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../Common/Documentation/Normal.xsl"?>

<cosydoc xmlns="urn:schemas-cosylab-com:Document">
	<head>
		<title>VisualDCT Release Notes</title>
		
		<info file="MEM-VisualDCT_Release_Notes"
			  url="http://visualdct.cosylab.com/builds/VisualDCT"
			  class="mem"
			  year="2002"
			  id="XX"
			  confidentiality="public"
			  project="VisualDCT"/>
			  
		<contributor name="Matej Sekoranja"
				id="msekoranja"
				email="matej.sekoranja@cosylab.com"/>

		<modification version="2.2.1236" by="msekoranja" date="2002-08-20">
			<section>Package B alpha integration build.</section>
		</modification>

		<modification version="2.3.1237" by="msekoranja" date="2002-10-20">
			<section>Package B release candidate.</section>
		</modification>

		<modification version="2.4.1244" by="msekoranja" date="2003-07-18">
			<section>Package C (full graphical hierarchy support) release candidate.</section>
		</modification>

		<modification version="2.4.1247" by="msekoranja" date="2003-12-28">
			<section>Minor bugfixes.</section>
		</modification>

		<modification version="2.4.1249" by="msekoranja" date="2004-03-30">
			<section>CapFast interoperability, minor bugfixes.</section>
		</modification>

		<modification version="2.4.1250" by="msekoranja" date="2004-08-30">
			<section>Package D1 release candidate.</section>
		</modification>

		<modification version="2.4.1256" by="msekoranja" date="2004-11-18">
			<section>Package D2 pre-release.</section>
		</modification>

                <modification version="2.4.1257" by="msekoranja" date="2005-05-27">
                        <section>Package D2 release.</section>
                </modification>

		<modification version="2.5.1271" by="msekoranja" date="2004-11-18">
			<section>Package F release.</section>
		</modification>

		<scope>
			This document is contains release notes of the current build.
		</scope>
		
		<audience>
			The audience of this document are all users of this VisualDCT build.
		</audience>
		
		<reference id="visualdct"
			   title="VisualDCT Project"
			   href="http://visualdct.cosylab.com/"
			   author="Matej Sekoranja"
			   date="2002"
			   publisher="Cosylab, Ltd."/>
			   
		<reference id="visualdct_latest"
			   title="VisualDCT latest build"
			   href="http://visualdct.cosylab.com/builds/VisualDCT/"
			   author="Matej Sekoranja"
			   date="2005"
			   publisher="Cosylab, Ltd."
			   revision="2.5.1271"/>

	</head>
	
	<body>
		<section id="noted" title="Release Notes">
			<p>
			Changes in current version:
<pre>
1. VISUALDCT V2.6 BUILD1274

1.1. OVERVIEW
VisualDCT package E (previouse version) implements advanced spreadseet support (try "View->Spreadsheet...").
VisualDCT package F implements basic multiple database file editing support.
Multiple db files are displayed using internal frames and support clipboard operations among them.


2. KNOWN ISSUES AND WORKAROUNDS

2.1. LIMITED GLOBAL OVERVIEW OF THE OPENED FILES
Most of the VDCT functionality, including spreadsheet view, search, inspectors and linking, works on the currently focused db.
More time needs to be spent on defining cross db use-cases to implement a more general and useful framework.

2.2. MACRO AND PORT CLIPBOARD OPERATIONS ARE NOT SUPPORTED
Macro and port objects for a template currently do not work correctly using cut/copy/paste operations.
The macros and ports should be added and removed using the popup menu. 

2.3. THE WORKSPACE BLINKS WHEN THE MAIN FRAME IS RESIZED
This seems to be an issue with Java rendering engine. A workaround is to upgrade to Java 1.6. 

2.4. SPREADSHEET DRAG AND DROP OPERATIONS BLOCK FOR 10 SECONDS OR MORE
This is an issue with older java 1.4 releases. To resolve this update your java 1.4 version to the latest (java 1.4.2_16).

2.5. OTHER ISSUES
o) loading a view while having another open at non-default zoom resets the zoom on that window
o) undoing port creation leaves the port in the template definitions
o) the internal frame is not redrawn after created or resize operation (Java 1.6 has this resolved)
o) plugins might need to be fixed for this version
</pre>
</p>
			<p>
			Disabilities/missing:
			<ul>
			  <li><kwd>include</kwd> statement is implemented, but saving files containing <kwd>include</kwd> statements 
			  	   will also include all the content of includes files.</li>
			  <li>multiple template definitions in one DB are not supported</li>
			  <li>user's manual to be completed</li>
			</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</cosydoc>
